all right here we are again these first
two programs are pretty Universal and if
you've never coded before at all um
write this day down because today is
your coding birthday and I used to
always tell people that actually wait
I'm trying to get the I'm trying to get
the the sainton like thing to work it's
not
working there it goes woohoo your coding
birthday because so we've just been
talking about coding up to now and now
you're going to actually write code all
right so open up that
file and let's put a program in there um
and you can see here whether of course I
told you I'm using the terminal
now um and we got my go we got my go mod
file there and we got my main.go file so
let's go ahead and add one now you can
just if you're using vim and you you
edit B.O it kind of cheats and tells you
what you need to have already but let's
let's do it hard way so I'm going to
remove it again so we're going to touch
M.O and then we're going to edit main.go
and we have suffixes on this not you
know how I hate them on Sal scripts but
on this kind of stuff we need them right
because we're going to be compiling this
and we have an empty file here so the
first thing in any go program is the
package line package Main and any
program has a package main any program
that runs must have a package main um um
so we need that and and in package main
every main package has to have a
function called
main this is similar to other languages
like C that have to have a main or or
Java or others that if you have a
runnable program uh you have a main in
Python you have a main too it's just
hidden from you usually so there's
almost always this idea of a main
function right um the first thing to
note here is that this isn't a function
and I I'm going to save my rant for that
till later uh for right now just just
write what it
says right and all you really need to do
think about right now is that the
instructions the commands that are going
to execute uh for this program go in
these go in between these curly brackets
which is called a block so put that in
your notes you want to write that in
your notes right now right block block
is anything between curly brackets Ino
okay in Python has anything that's all
indented to the same level in Java has
anything a curly brackets and see it's
anything in curly brackets you follow me
a block of code a block of code is
something a delimited block of of things
that run at the same level okay so in
this CA in this case we're putting it
here and uh we're going to actually put
our first sort of
contrived uh line here
and you might I'm going to actually do
something that most people don't do but
I want you to know this and you'll know
90% of the go programmers don't know
this um but if you put if you put print
in here and then inside of these
parentheses you put a word in double
quotes hello right hello friend right
whatever hello friend and you save that
first of all if you're using a any
decent editor and you save it it'll
automatically reformat for you and I
want you to see that it's actually
putting tabs here so standard go
requires tabs for indentation if for
some reason your editor is not doing
that you need to fix that right now
because otherwise you're going to be
really suffering um there's some
interesting things you can do here with
this I can actually put a semicolon here
because go has what's called automatic
semicolon insertion and which means that
there's actually semicolons that are
inserted at the end of the line it's a
part of the syntax you just don't ever
see it and but the reason that's
important is because it means you can do
silly things like this and then code
them and the formatter will know what to
do so like if I were to put another
print statement here print uh I don't
know again right this is completely
valid go code set no list see so it's
it's sorry it's hard to read but this is
completely valid go code a lot of people
don't know this right so if I save this
uh it will continue to put it on the
same line it's perfectly happy to do
that and so but you know we might not
want to do that right sometimes you
might sometimes you might not um I was
expecting it frankly to re to reformat
this which it normally will do uh
normally if you have a program like that
it will put them it'll automatically
reformat it and say nope you can't do
that I'm going to I'm going to make it
pretty for you and I'm going to put them
on separate lines okay so but it's not
I'm not doing that um semicolon means
new line yeah and so it's essentially
they're the same and um there the reason
I'm mentioning this is because as you
proceed it's your first coding language
I'm assuming and so as you proceed
learning other coding languages this is
something that's very significant
because there are many many other
languages that have semicolon insertion
including JavaScript um so a lot of
people don't know this but you don't
have to put semicolons at the end of
JavaScript there's a big thing about
that the entire Twitter codebase doesn't
have any semicolons um in JavaScript
because it's not required because of
automatic semicolon insertion which can
sometimes get you in trouble and I'll
leave that conversation for another day
that's a rabbit hole you can go down but
it would be remiss of me to not mention
it to you since this is your first time
coding um this idea of like having
commands per line you know you may have
learned to Shell Code a little bit you
already know about this I mean this is
again it's exactly the same thing on the
shell just as a reminder if you're if
you're coding on the shell and you want
to say while true do Echo hello friend
sleep for one second and then done you
can see it's exactly the same thing
every time there's a semicolon it
injects an extra line so when it comes
to Shell coating knowing about this you
know semicolon insertion you can use a
lineer a shell Coe is a valuable thing
because you're going to find yourself as
a you know somebody who's moving at
terminal velocity pluged for my other
book is you know is a way for you to go
start to do this right away by being
able to write lines on one line um it's
not as relevant for go obviously but it
is a thing so I just wanted to make you
aware of
that uh just a second and okay
so so we're going to go ahead and keep
going here now any go purist out there
see me using print here and they're like
what the hell Mr Rob why are you
teaching them a deprecated UNS Ed thing
I'm teaching it to you this way because
I want you to see that this is actually
a thing you can actually run this so how
would I run this all right so this is a
big part of this first lesson any hello
world uh equivalent always has this
right how do you run the code so you can
do there's like three different ways to
run it go run main. go which just runs
it and you notice it didn't put a line
return at the end right
interesting uh yeah so let's do that
let's change it instead of being a print
let's do print a len and that adds a
line return all right let's try that way
okay so now it prints them out on their
own line and you there's there's a lot
of go people who don't even know that
exists um and it's kind of a fun Legacy
uh reason for that existing um yeah I
don't first of all you see how this is
this is um this is green that's because
it's a keyword yeah so let me let me
show you how to really do this and those
of you who know about standard a and
standard out uh this is why I'm telling
you this because you'll already be that
much for ahead of everybody else if you
do it that way what happens if I
redirect standard
out right so I do go run and I'm going
to redirect uh standard error to Dev
null what do I get
nothing so already you're ahead of 90%
of go programmers because they don't
know this they don't know it they don't
know that there is a built-in keyword
called print alen and print for printing
things out to standard error by default
and they will use log. println and they
will use a whole bunch of other things
to do it and really you just want to be
able to write something really quickly
and have it loged out and you don't want
to have to go find it again and you want
to be able to remove those later from
your code so now you're already ahead
because now you can put these
willy-nilly in your code and then later
delete them in order while you're
debugging your code to find a problem
because they're not affecting your
output if you want to actually do this
right you can say this let's just do
this let's say debug debug hello
world uh you like the detail so debug
okay so you have so let's say debug
hello friend okay so now it's my debug
statement right but if you want to
actually print something out to the
screen uh you want to do fmt which is an
official package with a capital we're
going to talk about this but a capital P
print Ln and then you could say hello
print
right and now you've got your hello
friend uh we don't need that right there
and so here we go now we can run the
same thing it's it's going to look like
it's running it
twice right it looks like it ran it
twice but as you can see if you redirect
the errors to Dev null you only get the
one and if you redirect the standard
thing to null then it only prints debug
that's because you're printing out to
two two different streams you should
have already learned about these in your
shell coding but if you haven't then
these are called standard output and
standard error okay there are two
different streams of data that go to the
terminal right unless you redirect them
and again redirection is not
covered we're not covering redirection
that's all covered by terminal velocity
or someplace else but that's what we're
doing here right so it's you know we've
got errors going to one now why would
you ever ever use that as I already
mentioned because you might want to be
debugging something right and you might
want to see the value without having it
affect what's actually coming out of
your code and by the way if you ever
print debugging output to standard error
you should be fired on the spot I really
I really mean that I have had to deal so
often with people who who print
debugging code to standard output and
destroy the stuff that they're doing
it's absolutely it's one of the most
egregious sins against
terminal utility development ever and it
happens all the time um just don't do
that right so now you know have to do
while we're at it there is one other
thing that is required that I talk to
you about before we leave this
particular topic and that is log so if
you would rather do this in the way that
you're going to see for other people you
can use log pral it all right now this
log is an entire Library it's actually
it's actually now uh a cover on top of
something called SL log which is super
amazing not at all in the scope of this
book but now you know it exists and what
that does is that that is the proper way
um to write something to standard error
now you can totally change this when you
do it this way you get quite a bit uh
different uh Behavior because now you
get a date stamp with it and you can
play with it in all kinds of different
ways and um and and that's really a
better way to do it but I but it would I
can't cover print without showing you
that print L and print exist and that
you can throw them in there if you
really want to or you can just type this
um I actually have a bimm macro that is
like liter M and it automatically just
puts lint print made it to there I just
I put this in all the time I put it into
things like if I need to make what you
know where I got there was a there was a
stack exchange survey that asked what
the number one debugging uh ideer method
was and the overwhelming response I
think it was like 80% was print
statements because you know even the the
most seasoned Veterans of US unless
we're doing like really low level kernel
development where we have to walk
through a complicated algorithm or
something you know we're usually using
print um especially C Cy you know um we
are you know we're software Engineers
but we're not to that degree we just
want to get stuff done so so that
hopefully will will guide you um let's
actually deconstruct all the components
of this so you can understand what is
we're talking about some of these things
we're going to be coming back and we're
going to be talking about a lot so this
idea of function here um this this idea
of like parentheses what's going on with
that this is where normally you'll pass
arguments through parameters which you
don't know about yet um and this here is
an argument that's going into this print
Allin function um I one of the things I
don't like about um about a real
language like go is that I have to jump
right into these topics right away I
can't easy into it like I could with
python um because or shell right um and
and I I I want to just make a comparison
to show really quickly just this one
time so you can see what I'm talking
about so uh there is in Shell there is a
print command it's called print F uh
there's also an echo command which is
basically print l n and you can say
hello friend and you can just write it
right from the command line and it does
the same thing as this program that we
just wrote you're like why are we
writing a full-blown program just to
print hello world when I could do it in
one line from the command line good
question probably a bad idea but there
is you know when we start to look at a
real language like this we start to look
at these things but what I want to show
here is that the concepts that we're
going to be learning in go about
variables and everything apply to the
Shell they apply to everything that
you're ever going to use so we're going
to talk about them in that way without
getting really deep into the Weeds on
these other things now is it true that
Echo does doesn't have this
yes right friend
whoops um you know yeah I could run a
pearl program that does the same thing
right I could say pearl d e print uh
hell friend you know and I could get
that you notice it doesn't print a line
return there so I could change it to say
they change it to the word say and
that'll do the same thing no quotes
there the point is is this is transvers
able and it it's all over the place um
that's the main takeaway so and in every
case we have to talk about something
right away uh which is arguments and
parameters and um so this is these are
words to put in your notes okay so
arguments and parameters and if you've
had algebra you've already talked about
this before um and you know if if like
if you were to say you know xal 2 y you
know to Y to to let's see y equal sorry
y = 2x uh + 3 or something you know
what's going on with that right H you
would know that this is also you could
say you could say f ofx equals whatever
you can't actually code like that but
the point is is that this is the idea
when they do F ofx you see that right
there it could do this too I could do F
of XY and I could have uh uh you know
plus uh
plus uh 5 + 4 Y and then this is the
concept make sure this gets into your
notes my friends okay this is one of
those places where computer science
directly correlates to mathematics if
you've had linear algebra a lot of this
is going to make uh my my my son and I
actually did an informal analysis of
what what allowed young people to get
coding faster than anybody else some of
them struggled some of them didn't and
overwhelmingly the ones who had had
linear algebra got it they just were
able to understand arguments with
parameters and this you know the idea of
breaking down equations and as well as
steps and but what I'm trying to show
you here is that these two things X and
Y F of X and Y the X and the Y are
parameters so write that down okay
parameters are named
variables that have scope to the
function in this case in which they
belong
okay so parameters are scoped input
data for a particular block of code of
some kind okay that's what they are and
in this case in this in this in this
linear algebra equation sort of thing I
don't even know if it's linear algebra
anymore um now we
have um yeah so we have an X and A Y
right and the the values that go into
those parameters are called arguments
this gets people mess this up all the
time I've heard veteran Educators get
this wrong okay uh yeah Mad Libs game is
a great way to do it we're going to do
that later yeah it also teaches
templates so that's a great suggestion
um we are going to do that so for right
now though you just need to understand
that the arguments are the things that
go into the parameter variables and then
the parameter variables are visible
within usually just the scope of the
Block in the function or whatever that
they sub rtin that they were that they
were put into so now you know please
make sure that gets in your notes that
is really really important uh we're not
going to talk about variable scope just
yet but just know that that's what we're
talking about okay and um why why is
that relevant because you know this
concept doesn't apply just to numbers it
applies to other things other types okay
so now we have to talk about types and
this is one of the reasons that we are
doing go okay one of the reasons to do
go right off the bat is because we get
to use types okay and types are a core
part of any computer programming
language anywhere and whether they're
implicit they're loose they're strict
whatever they're a thing and go is
perfect the perfect Goldilocks language
to introduce you to the concept of typed
data okay okay so what have we talked
about so far we've been throwing around
this thing with double quotes around it
it's let's just let's like call it what
it is it's called a string and if you
want to have someplace to I used to have
a a thing that I would show where it was
actually a necklace and I had a knot on
both sides you can think of the quotes
on either side of a string as being
holding together a bunch of beads and
the beads are letters and numbers on the
string okay that's a string and you you
cut one of those knots off and all the
stuff falls off right and you get help
with that you know you cut one of those
off and you got an IDE helping you out
um it's going to yell at you it's like
no no I don't know what to do H right so
um so some of you may already know
strings from another language so let me
just clarify really quickly and go about
strings and how they work um so yeah
we'll do we're going to do a calculator
function later when we cover functions
we haven't covered that yet yeah so so
the next thing we're going to cover is
we've got these this string here so this
is an ARG it's a single argument it's a
string but it's got these double quotes
in it right so there are another there
are a couple other ways to do this the
other one is a back tick and the only
thing right now to take away from that
is the back tick allows you to put line
returns in your code um so go run may
not go and it it just respects the line
returns in there right um You don't know
about escapes yet but I'm going to show
you one kind of ahead of time when you
have a double quote you can't do that it
will yell at you and say you can't do
that some of you who code in Shell or
python or something like that's weird it
is it's different than those other
languages it's not allowed so uh if you
want to do that same thing you'd have to
put a backs sln which is an escape uh
and then that will get you what you
wanted um uh and you know there are
several escapes which we'll get to more
in later but I just wanted you to see
that um by the way this Ln this this
back slash n might as well cover it's
called a line feed a Line Feed and it
relates to the teletype machine so in a
nutshell all terminals are teletype
machines in fact they're still called
TyTy lsdev
TyTy there's still a bunch of TTY
devices on every Unix system and Linux
and everything because they are teletype
machines and you're going to see a lot
of similarities to the teletype machine
Line Feed right uh you know the the the
the the the sending of characters that
set the state of your terminal like
changing the color of the printer these
are all things that we're going to deal
with a lot uh there's another one by the
way it's called a carriage return might
as well talk about it a carriage return
it used to be there's been big fight in
history I won't get really long into it
but um you'll often see line feeds
followed by a carriage return because
strictly speaking that's how you get the
the you know the carriage to the where
it needs to start printing next but
because for many reasons over time
historically uh everybody has just
settled on Line Feed only as opposed to
carage turn Line Feed there's a couple
of significant exceptions to that one of
them is the internet so HTTP the
hypertex transfer protocol which you
eventually will get into it requires a
carriage return line feed at the end of
every line so this what we're talking
about here is line endings and we're not
going to dwell on it too much more than
that but just know that it's a thing and
that it's radically different depending
on what operating system you're on in
fact git and GitHub go to Great Lengths
to make sure that the code that you use
is downloaded in the right way so that
when you edit it it ends up going back
up into GitHub with the proper line
endings because and to summarize Windows
is finally changed this but Windows is
Windows puts only carriage return at the
end no windows puts carries return line
return line feed at the end uh Mac put
only line return at the end uh Carri
return at the end and Unix only put Line
Feed at the end for years years and
years and years and they only now are
finally coming together and saying Kua
and everything so if if you've ever had
a deal with a file um that had weird
line endings on it now you know why um
and we can't get away from talking about
Carriage CL without talking about the
TTY and those things if you want to go
down a really fun Rabbit Hole go
research the in the creation of the
first terminal we're using a terminal
right here but it's also important that
pedantically I tell you right now we are
not using a terminal we are using a
terminal emulator that's the ex that's
the official name for what we're using
here all of these things are terminal
emulators Because the actual terminal
would be a terminal it would be
connected to the teletype machine and
and a in fact some people use the
teletype machine itself as a terminal
there was no screen when they first came
out they would do all these same things
and they'd wait for it to type and then
they would type their next line item
thing it's pretty cool anyway so um this
Ln right here is really just shorthand
we're going to get rid of this log one
this Ln right here is just is really
just shorthand for doing the same exact
thing that we just did why is that
important if you're coming from Pearl or
something like that you know that you
have to put this stuff at the end of a
string or it won't print uh oops that's
kind of noisy thank you for the fall so
let's um if we do this hello friend you
see it's the same thing right so so just
to make it easy uh they went ahead and
add a print Ln this is a really common
convention from the C language as well
there's there's usually Ln uh options
for anything that prints to the terminal
and there are some pretty substantial
reasons you would not want to put a line
in return so like if you're trying to
make it a part of a of a of a program
that's going to be output and captured
into a variable and shell you might not
want that so just know about it um uh I
actually have created a
um I created a a version of print called
uh term print that does the right thing
and I'm just going to put a plug for it
um you don't have to use it but it's in
my bons library and what it it actually
does the right thing depending on how
it's used so what this does is like when
I run go run main.go
right uh oopsie go get that's you by the
way if you I'm you're not supposed to do
this yet but if you add a dependency
you're going to need to that we'll cover
out later so anyway here we go go run
main you see how it puts hell friend
like that but when I when I do it when I
make it output to a pipe it does not put
the line
return so so that's that's why the the
it's back slash in and not forward slash
in yeah that goes inside the quotation
marks because the quotation marks are
the quotation marks the the line return
itself is a part of the string and
that's really important to understand is
that it is a part of the string okay so
this this is uh but what I was trying to
show you is that there are times like
when you want to use the output as a
value someplace and you don't want that
line return um then you need to get you
know you're enjoying it okay so um you
definitely want to do that and if you if
you want a variation of print which is
this is what it is by the way um this is
my variation of print print calls print
Ln if it is interactive otherwise it's
just regular print this works in better
complications applications that would
need to trim the trailing variable okay
so
um makes a yes let's talk about that
thank you that's a good reminder Elite
so one last thing to talk about here um
so we'll go back to FNP this is
automatically going to use the standard
FNP Bonsai is a that's my thing if you
if you make that you'd have to depend on
my my project which is not going
anywhere but still um the P why is the P
capitalize like every other language
would never put an initial Capital this
is a very unique go thing that when you
when people first hear about it myself
included they get a little bit put off
by it and I want to talk to you about
this so in other languages um rather
than have a an you know an identifier
like this it would be lowercase and when
somebody created it they would have to
declare how the thing uh behaved and
we're not ready to get into variable and
function declaration just yet but just
know that by it being an initi Capital
what it's saying is that the fmt package
and I'll show you where it's defined did
you see what I just did by the way I'm
going to I'm going to show you some
there's a couple VI things I just did a
g d so a GD will jump to the definition
of that that program in its location in
code I don't know that you can actually
do that in BS code it's one of the
reasons I prefer the terminal so I'm
actually reading the source code that
defined the print statement for go and
you can see right here that it's says
print formats blah blah blah it tells
you what it does here's the print
statement here's the arguments which we
we're going to understand all that later
but you can see what what's going on
here right but but but rather than
saying and I I this is this change is
not going to stick but if I were to say
rather than having it be like local or
exported you know exported or blah blah
blah like you would CNC or C++ or Java
or everything else pretty much
JavaScript Ruby rust they all have have
these like convoluted ways of telling
you who can see this thing who can use
it and then go Pike this is Pike's idea
and I got to tell you it you know at
first it might strike people the wrong
way but I it is it is absolute genius
they have decided that if you make the
first letter uppercase it's
automatically got an exported or a
public scope so that means anybody else
can see it anybody else who has an
import St like this to import my module
this is main they probably wouldn't do
that but if they were to import it they
could import the statement and they can
use it if it's not uppercase they can't
use it that means it's private so if
you've used any other languages that's
what's going on okay um yeah yeah it's
there are a lot of people who have come
from other languages who really hate
this uh I definitely think this
qualifies as one of Ryan doll's cute
things that you later regret uh Ryan a
node developer obviously the creator of
node but uh he says that in his famous
10 Things I Hate About node speech uh
don't do those cute things don't do
those things I do feel like this is a
little cute um however I'm not opposed
to it I use it all the time the only
time this becomes a major problem is
when we start dealing with structures
and whether they're visible or not and
how they are mapped to Json data which
is getting way ahead of ourselves but
later on we're going to get get to it
and that becomes a pain because now you
have to you can't it it you'll see it
becomes a pain and I feel like you know
I wouldn't have minded putting like you
know exported or something here I think
that would have been fine um in C you'll
see like public void main uh or
something like that right um so so there
you go uh if you don't know at first if
the thing should be public then yeah so
so that's so you'll see that main is
private obviously because that's not
getting exported but um when we start
making our own functions we're going to
assume that they are private uh by
default and then it you know we'll
export them and make it so that other
people can use them later but we're way
ahead of ourselves on that because we're
not ready to do that yet we're not even
ready to make a module yet we're just
starting out but it it is important that
you understand why that letter is a p
there now again go with its fm. print
has really pulled me into explaining a
bunch of things that incrementally might
have been easier to get to in a in a
slower way so for example if I was doing
the same code in Python um let's do that
for a second so um if I was going to
do uh main.py which whatever so if we
were going to do main.py you know we
would just uh we don't even have to do
that we can just say print you know
hello friend
and call it a day right and let do
Python 3 p you know we're done and so
because python same with pearl uh is
already got an implicit main function
around it right so this is one of the
reasons people like teaching python
first because I could just show you this
and you would be like oh okay and you
know we could just talk about those
things that to tell you about exported
and Main and packages and all that jazz
um yeah this definitely yeah yeah that's
that's that's worth saying so before we
leave this topic um this is this is how
you would do it in Java and this is if
you're in computer science uh AP
Computer Science in America you you are
being taught this instead as your very
first thing
so wait wait wait should we write it in
Java let's actually write it in Java
yeah so the Java version would be main.
Java it would be uh public what is it
public static void
main string and you have to put all of
these things on there string args uh and
then you
know yeah and then it would
be we'll get to that yeah so you know
you this is the same
thing what is it in C C is
like it's it's not much better right
so I'm only doing that to show you how
much better go is than those other
languages I mean for that kind of thing
some people would say they like that but
I don't I don't like it modern Java
doesn't modern recent Java doesn't
require this anymore interesting seems
like it's getting blunted in temp plus
C++ is crazy yeah so I mean the point of
that little rabbit hole is just to tell
you that go was one of the first
languages to say now we want some we're
going to stay we're a real language
we're compiled in everything we're
compatible with C we're faster than C
we're faster at running than python even
in run mode um but we're we're going to
get rid of some of these other things
and we're going to make it feel like
Python and that's why I love it so much
is it it I really I call it the goldilux
language because I think it hits you
perfect Middle Ground uh between C uh or
you know rust is very much in the C in
terms of complexity and Python and if
you read about Rob Pike and their design
goals uh at Google the goal was for and
I quote beginner programmers to be able
to pick it up quickly and so they they
kept it simple and unsexy and you know
for a reason because they wanted it to
be easy to write okay a couple other
things before we before we leave hello
world and hello friend um up here is the
package that was up that was imported um
most of the stuff uh is needing to be
imported including the basic stuff I did
a print all end when it didn't do that
um that's a key word it it came very
early in the language it's since been
deprecated nobody uses it but it's still
there if you want to use it um and
you'll notice that when I added the log
here this is very important so if I add
log as soon as I saved it
uh uh rust rust is well for the function
declaration yes but when it comes to
types later it's a little bit more
harder um but yeah so but uh but
foro when I don't know if you notice
this but when I saved you see when I
saved it and I used the log package the
the bmgo automatically adds I think it's
go importer actually it automatically
adds these and let me let me show what
happens if you don't have one it well
it'll add it it won't let me not save it
now but if you don't have something that
will keep your import statements up to
date you are going to go crazy for the
first year that I wrote this code I did
not know about this and I had to
constantly so like if you if you want to
just temporarily turn something off like
that and you still have log up here it
won't run it won't even compile because
go is really really pedantic about that
it's like no you are not using this you
so you should not I'm not even going to
compile because you're not going to
wastefully import a thing because the
people who made go were like so hellbent
on keeping the code clean so they won't
even let you import a thing unless you
use the thing it's uncompilable code you
know it won't even compile so I I think
that's wonderful um but it's you know
it's uh it's it's kind of a pain when
you're switching back and forth so
unless you have the automatic import
Porter on which I of course now do have
uh when you save you're you're going to
go crazy okay so just know about that um
something else that just fun fact is
that the reent package and import are at
the beginning of everything unlike C is
because this dramatically increases the
speed with which they can parse the code
and compile because they they can now
stop after the first import section as
soon as they get past the import section
in the constant section I think they can
stop parsing the thing completely they
don't have to parse anything else in the
file and if you know about C you know
about how bad C macros are and how how
how crazy they can get and um that's not
a thing in go and that was why go was
made the way it was it's also the reason
that even if you use fmt in 10 places in
different files or whatever um you have
to put the import statement in every one
of them and that was that was a
concession that the go designer said so
that the code would compile fast and go
hands down to this day is the fastest
comp comp has the fastest language
compilation of any language in history
which is pretty amazing and you know it
was actually made by a guy who who was
around when Richie made C he was one of
his friends so it's no surprise that you
know compilation that Pike jokes all the
time that go was conceived while they
were waiting for C++ to compile at
Google so you know but but now you know
what's going on with the import there
okay uh pack made a special case with c
and only package can have a main
function yes you can only have one main
function we did talk about that um you
only get one you only get one main
function in the whole program okay and
everything else has to be has to be put
in if you have two of them it won't
compile uh can you have a package
function yes you can um we're not ready
to do those yet but we are going to
start writing our own functions pretty
soon uh in Windows Windows registry
points to particular file registry keys
and I can find so many crash entries
where package were uninstalled yes yeah
because and so this idea of like
removing a thing and then having it be
cleaned up automatically it won't
compile love it right that just every
time I would run into one of these
design things um you know with the
exception of the cute you know exporter
thing um I would be impressed I would
come away being you know like Color Me
impressed this is this is somebody who
really knows what they're doing and they
have they put satellites into orbit they
made unic code they made their own
operating system it's not some
accidental language that somebody just
thought they would be try to fun to try
out which pretty much describes most of
the other languages out there uh that
unfortunately goes being compared to um
anyway so let's do this um so we've got
strings we've got our hello world friend
our hello friend and we've talked about
our first type so somebody asked about
this how would I print numbers
here and this is where we have uh uh you
know our first Divergence
from scripting right a scripting
language would be totally fine with this
this is not going to compile uh actually
it will but it's not going to be what
you think yeah this is kind of let's run
this
whoops G run main.go yeah we're I'm
getting tired wait
what
what that's not supposed to
work what I just learned something
oh my God I just learned something about
go that's not supposed to
work they changed it when did they
change it did they make peral in take a
generic
now oh my
Lord
they that is new you guys that is
totally new oh I'm so glad I found
that it's got to be taken to generic
now you guys don't know what that is yet
but they
did oh no it's always been an any okay
never mind never mind never mind all
right all right all right I'm sorry I
got excited I I don't ever do
that okay so print is a special print is
special print will take whatever the
type is that's what this is about we're
going to learn about this later print
will take one or more of a thing and it
will print whatever type it is as a
string try that and
see
that that is I'm still kind of reeling
from that because
[Music]
uh yeah I was not expecting that to work
watch watch watch so okay okay so we
could do this this is this is particular
for this for this
thing yeah I wonder if I can try a let's
let's try the other
ones yeah I I didn't realize I didn't
realize it had the type inference that
deep in there I guess it's always had
it but I mean it it obviously has
because I've I've done this before I put
like a value at the end of it right okay
so this is a good chance to kind of like
look at the different types okay so if
you've coded in any other language then
you know about the different types we're
going to cover the three basic um some
people call primitive types okay um and
quite frankly a string is really not a
primitive um a string is is in C is a
character array in other words it's it's
a bunch of of character types and go
they're called runes usually um and
they're joined together right so a
string is not technically A Primitive
type but in Python you may have worked
with strings in a JavaScript most
interpreted languages shell languages
like that they pretty much only have
three or four types so let's talk about
what those types are right away all
right so they are they are Boolean true
or false they are numbers integers you
know usually in most interpreted
languages it's a number right and in
some of them distinguish between a
floating Point number which has a
decimal in it you know a DOT and then
those that don't
um but they are different types not only
are they type different types they're
significantly different types and we'll
get to that in a second
um because you know reasons right so um
and then what other types do we have so
we also have we have the string we
already talked about that we have
Boolean or false um we have we're
talking like primitive types uh we have
we have numbers in this case we have two
of those we actually have much much more
than those but most people will know
integers uh in case you're wondering
shell does not do anything floating
Point only integers you can force zshell
to use a floating point but you
shouldn't because it's unexpected no
shell has ever done that but in go
you've got you know real math and
everything you can do here um and you
know you can actually do some math here
and and have it print out um and and you
know so you know you got everything um
the other uh so we have numbers we have
booleans and we have uh strings but but
strings as I said are made up of other
things so what what are they actually
yes we have complex for numerics and a
bunch of things not ready for those yet
so we're still just using the basic
types that they would have got from
python or JavaScript um and the other
one is a single character okay otherwise
known as the Rune um and we're going to
get way way into the these later when we
talk when we're going to make a program
that that converts um words into binary
which is kind of fun because you can
write code for your friends and thing um
it's actually not really hard it's a
oneliner uh but I'll show it it to you
later so if I put the letter H here um
you can see that it'll print the number
72 and you're like what's going on with
that well that's because we're now
looking at each one of those individual
characters or runes sh is a word from C
which doesn't apply to go and we're
going to talk about why that is uh the
word the proper word and go is a rune
and the difference between a sh and a
rune for those who care for now is that
a rune is a Unicode code point and a sh
is
an8 bit
sh okay so um yeah definitely in fact we
can actually print the lowercase one
right next to it and you'll see that
they are different numbers and if you
look up those numbers on the asky
character table you'll see that that's
what they are and if you don't know
about the asy character table um you can
run man
asky and it will show you the asy
character table um so there is there's
Capital H it looks like 110 maybe I got
this
wrong did I get it wrong
did I get it wrong Capital H and lower
case h I might have got it wrong so uh
yeah so the other thing too and L I'm
just going to mention this now is all
the range operators assume unic code
code points um 110 D okay 110 yeah I'm
wondering if I got that right I might
have told you wrong so what is why is
here and that's that's the this is the
integer
value of of that's it's not asky
apparently so I got that wrong somehow I
I we'll look it up later we'll look it
up later I I've got it I got it wrong
yeah what it's doing though is it's
telling you that the it might it might
be
um it's not B heex is it well we'll get
back to it later I'm way ahead of
myself so these things are numbers when
you when you take a character and use
single quotes not back ticks single
quotes you are now doing you can do utf8
and all kinds of stuff yes so again
we're getting way ahead of ourselves we
have an entire activity dedicated to uh
understanding characters and how how
they're actually numbers underneath the
hood and everything so I don't want to
get that far ahead right now um but just
the takeaway here is that these are
different types and and you can see that
there's there's this idea of like one
type could actually be another type and
you know spoiler alert everything is a
one or a zero
at the end of the day every single thing
is a one or a zero by the end of the day
and and and I'm going to jump ahead and
show you something kind of cool here
right so if you want to see the binary
of these we're going to make a whole
program on this but it'll be a fun thing
to end on if you want to change any of
these things to their binary value
instead of doing print we're going to do
print F okay print F we we kind of
learning print here so what does print F
do print F lets you put a a whole format
here uh for how to the thing should be
output okay and um it's kind of if we're
going to cover print Ln and everything
else we might as well cover print F okay
so print F takes whatever this thing is
over here and injects it into the format
now if you're in Python use f strings
are called and javascript's got them all
they're all different colors different
kinds and and you know live will use
print F from the shell and you'll
recognize it it's not an S it's a V and
this is a go thing so go has several
print app things that you can use many
of which are consistent with the
standard original C print app which is
where it all came from uh but you can
actually put this now you got to make
sure to put a line return here be a line
feed sorry because it won't do it if you
don't have it um and we'll do those okay
so so there you go and now we can
actually run this so we're still doing
go run for now but you see It'll it
still does the same thing right and what
I'm trying to show you here is that when
you do a println it's doing this on each
thing it's it's doing this and so the V
means we can think of it as verbose but
what it means is what is the String
representation of this type and so it
actually in the case over here it
converts a Boolean true into to the
string t r e and then prints it out
that's what V does okay so V says and
this is something it's very uniquely go
that I love I absolutely love it every
single type in go by
default has a string
representation so the reason this is
printing is because the string
representation of true is the string
true and the string representation of
the number one of the integer 1 2 3 4 is
the string 1 2 3 4 and if you if you've
done any coding in any other language
you you realize how big a deal that
is because you would have to write you
know you'd have to convert it to a
string you have to write your own
conversions and everything to get it
even print again the Goldilocks of
languages the perfect you know just just
complex enough but not too complex so
there's some cool things you can do with
this here and I'm not going to you're
going to have to go read about it if you
by the way every time I do that I'm
pushing capital K on top of the thing
and then I'm just uh whoops I'm pushing
whenever time I want to read on the
thing V is for visual um it yep and it
works for strs it works for everything
it works for arrays we haven't got to
complex types please don't let's don't
go there yet uh even yes even the types
you create Hab a representation by
default and spoiler alert you can set
the string formatter interface you can
implement it and in include your own
string representations for your own
types so if you want your type to be
represented as Json you can override the
string form matter method pretty damn
cool I can't wait to show you so but
before we leave this this topic of of
cool print F stuff that you can do
obviously you can put another thing here
we're sticking with primitive types for
now strings characters numbers blah blah
blah um uh you can actually do Emojis
too so actually let me let me Let's do
an emoji
um Let's do let's do hello let's do uh
what's what's uh Let's do let's do a
world Emoji so the inventor of go is
also the inventor of Unicode so it has
full support for utf8 in the language in
fact you can name your identifiers
emojis if you want to I don't know why
you would do that but you
can so you can do all kinds of crazy
things so let's say see if this will
print out let's see what that says um
and that prints it out just fine if you
know what the value is for that which I
don't but you know what we can do we can
trick it let's make it print it as a
number
yeah uh is it
n oh I think it's
I I can't remember which one is oh it's
not I by the way if you try to use
something you see that error I got
that's because I is not a thing
I thought it was
in it what is it is it f I can't
remember all only real Chads use emojis
for
naming what how am I spacing that it's
not s it's not
S no s s just writes it out as a as a
string that for is in a
string well I'm GNA have to go read
about him all right so I did I C let's
go look I have to look it up I don't
remember
uh print out the formats blah blah
blah B encounter that's that doesn't
give me everything I want
though
huh I can't remember the N what is it I
thought it was
I is it an
integer I'm using the
latest I started a macro on accident God
I'm I'm totally spacing this I can't
remember it
I thought I well I know F okay let's use
f it's youu you're right it is you
because it's in it's in and it's n and
everything okay f is the floating Point
[Music]
number it's not it's not
F oh it's like I can't convert this all
right all right all right right it's
like you can't do an F okay let's do
Unicode oh it's the wrong type oh I see
what's up
okay there's capital u
too yeah that's the unic code one yeah
that's the one I was looking for yeah
okay thank you for the reminder okay but
that's a Okay the reason it's failing is
because it's a string so a string is
more than one of the thing so if I want
to fix this I have to put it in single
quotes and now it should work although
it was still yelling at me no okay now
it should give us the Unicode character
so there you go there's the Unicode Cod
Point okay and you can do the reverse of
this right so you can do the reverse
this and I we're getting way ahead of
ourselves but um so that's the unod code
point for if you want to see the unic
point you just put the U in front and
there's heximal and there's all we're
going to get all to that all that later
but but you know you can do some pretty
cool things here so like another way you
could do this if you really wanted um is
you know you could say V and you could
change this to be the unic code C Point
uh which which which was it I don't
remember so I'm going to go get it
okay so let's do
ah
whoopsie why why aren't you
pasting gosh dang
it I should make a program that does it
to just oh there we go okay so um
illegal Rune it doesn't like it more
than one character in The in R
literal character in R literal oh it's a
literal that's right I forgot about
this unexpected blah blah
blah I don't do oh wait is it
backslash I haven't done I'm getting way
ahead of
myself
there I could of SW is is it not
single one character in run little
in room later
on is it just
you is it SP SL
you I don't remember I don't write these
all the time I don't remember I should
know this I don't know it I would
fail I don't I don't think it's because
it's a
string I I think you can actually put as
a string like
this no I think it's
I can't remember I feel so bad oh wait
that's apparently going to be
okay oh that's that's not what we wanted
that's the
string I'm way ahead of myself but I got
to
[Laughter]
know oh print Unicode code point oh I'm
so sorry guys is it I don't it is
backslash yeah
I'm sorry I have to bail I have to
remember it's it's really specific to go
and I obviously I don't do this very
much um it is dasu okay there's there's
SLU and there's slash capital u yeah
yeah yeah yeah I screwed up so slash you
and slash capital
u I think I need to make it a lowercase
U actually yep I do that's what's going
on on oh I know what it is it's because
it's a u that means I have to put 00 Z
here yeah all right now remember whoa I
don't feel so bad that is hard to
remember all right so capital u means
it's in the higher order of Unicode
which we're getting way up Bas
here and and because it has one F
because it's an emoji it has a one in it
so it's in the range that's way above
you know the certain number and that's
why I had to put you have to put the
other zeros there and if you know my my
editor I started to remember it as I
started doing it my editor will tell you
how many zeros if you don't if you have
don't have enough zeros like thing okay
so I'm so
sorry but now you know right so um you
know that's the that's that's the way to
do it uh I I wish it would be a direct
one toone translation that would have
been cooler right but no so uh so so
there you go um okay now you see how I
put V put the put the number now if I I
can actually force that to a
string I'm pretty sure I can force it to
a string maybe I can't maybe I can't
force it to a
string no it's going to be it gave me my
the UTF the UTF
address yeah it's like one 1
f30e 1
f30e what's that for a single code AR
you cannot use a single character
variable in its place for substitute
when it asks for a single code
Rune um you can you can you can actually
you can say I want this to be a
string that's another thing we haven't
got there yet but this
is yeah there see that you see how it
prints the world
now yeah so
um that's way more than we ever we
supposed to cover right
now we'll get there but the last one
that I wanted to show you this is the
fun
one uh this is casting we're going to
get into casting you can actually you
can actually take certain things and say
I want you to treat it like this instead
we we'll get to that I promise this is
the kind of thing we could never cover
well python covers it a little bit but
um so watch this though let's let's take
hello friend you want to make a secret
message to your friend this is very
uniquely go you can change the entire
hello friend string to Binary just by
changing it to a b b type output and um
so yeah I'm going to try to see if I can
get it to do the binary one I it might
it might be capital
B uh what is print F goang binary I
think it's Capital it might be capital
B yeah it's you have to turn it into a
bite slice I think you do
I have to turn it into I think I have to
turn it into an array of bites yes I do
okay so you don't know about this yet
but but I I just want to show it to you
and then and then I'll end because we're
way over already it's exactly one hour
here so um let's change this to say I
want it to be instead of treating it as
a string let's treat it as a whole bunch
of bites that are that are that are
associated that are one come one after
the other this is called an array you
don't know that yet but these are like
you want to look at it as indiv ual
bites and um that should yeah there's
our binary right so yeah you can put
that hold together and you can turn it
into binary and we're going to actually
do that we're going to make a program
that does that we're going to do xod
decimal you tip eight all the stuff and
it's if you're just doing this for fun
um you're going to learn a lot about how
computers work the same reason a lot of
people learn C so they can understand
how the computers work but um in kind of
a fun way plus it's also fun if you just
want to make you know simple rot 13
rotation you know things and uh codes
for your friends and everything like
that so um so that's coming we're going
to do that next um we we we did briefly
talk about variables but the next hour
we're going to talk about variables and
we're going to talk about um the complex
types the types that are collections of
other types and um we're going to hit
that pretty heavy before we move on from
that uh and then and then we'll we'll do
the other traditional things because
because you'll see how types can really
affect everything that it's all about
the data at the end of the day um and so
yeah this is hopefully this has been uh
a lot for you yeah I'm I'm not going to
be able to do another one tonight so I
will be doing uh another two or three
videos tomorrow and we'll we'll go on
from there um but you know give this a
try let's go ahead and save it let's
save our work for for now um what's that
maybe I miss it but keep briefing what
type definitions are going after the
name
declaration
um there are none right now we haven't
you're talking about up
here yeah there this this is just a
function we haven't talked about type
definitions at all we also haven't
talked about variables we've just talked
about the three main types all right and
we're we're going to talk about
functions as a type to which is really
fun so there's there's
there's basically three main types for
everybody to to grock right now and I
showed you there's many many many others
but right now the three main types that
you should memorize are strings numbers
and booleans true or false that's it
okay and you know there we've seen how
those types are composed of other types
and those types are also other types at
the same time something that can be a
string and it can also be a number at
the same time I know it blows your mind
right we're going to cover that a lot
more tomorrow but um tomorrow we're
going to cover complex types which is
what this is this bite here this is a
collection you know of other tiny types
the other little um runes that we talked
about which you don't know about yet but
we'll learn about that tomorrow a rune a
rune is really great because as you
already saw a rune is a
letter and a number and in some cases it
can be treated as a Boolean all at the
same time and so you know how we look at
data differently is going to be a huge
theme
tomorrow and um is that is I'm really
excited if you can't tell because this
is the first time I've really been able
to dig into to to to this idea um
because when you learn JavaScript or
python as a language you really can't
you really can't understand this concept
as directly because those languages hide
this complexity from you in Mya in my
opinion
unnecessarily and um we'll talk about
that tomorrow I'm really having a hard
time not talking about it right now
because I love it this is great stuff so
we'll see you later